<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Supports | Krishnakant Saboo</title>
    <link>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Supports</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://kvsaboo.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Supports</title>
      <link>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Alzheimer&#39;s disease</title>
      <link>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/alz_details/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/alz_details/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Alzheimer’s disease progresses over decades, but symptoms manifest only in the advanced stages, which makes early diagnosis and thereby, timely intervention difficult. The complexity and heterogeneity of the disease; sparse longitudinal data; and unknown relationships among factors such as disease pathology, brain structures, brain activity, and cognition present significant challenges in predicting disease progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have developed models that provide a holistic view of disease progression by combining ML with multimodal data and clinical domain knowledge in the form of science-based differential equations (DEs). Basing the model on DEs provides biological interpretability to the results and using ML improves the model&amp;rsquo;s data fitting capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The models predict personalized 5- to 10-year future cognitive decline in older adults, thus providing a tool to identify at-risk individuals. Our methods have also yielded novel insights into the physiological basis of compensatory processes that mitigate the effect of disease on cognition. Further investigation of these can guide the development of interventions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selected relevant publications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, C. Hu, Y. Varatharajah, S. A. Przybelski, R. I. Reid, C. G. Schwarz, J. Graff-Radford, D. S. Knopman, M. M. Machulda, M. M. Mielke, R. C. Petersen, P. M. Arnold, G. A. Worrell, D. T. Jones, C. R. Jack Jr., R. K. Iyer*, P. Vemuri* (2022). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1053811922001495&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Deep learning identifies brain structures that predict cognition and explain heterogeneity in cognitive aging&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NeuroImage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, A. Choudhary, Y. Cao, G. A. Worrell, D. T. Jones, R. K. Iyer (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://proceedings.neurips.cc/paper/2021/hash/af1c25e88a9e818f809f6b5d18ca02e2-Abstract.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Reinforcement learning-based disease progression model for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;NeurIPS&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, C. Hu, Y. Varatharajah, P. Vemuri, R. K. Iyer (2020). &lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/abstract/document/9098511&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Predicting longitudinal cognitive scores using baseline imaging and clinical variables&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;IEEE International Symposium on Biomedical Imaging&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;ISBI&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;. (Oral presentation).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Epilepsy</title>
      <link>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/epilepsy_details/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/epilepsy_details/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Roughly 30% of epilepsy patients do not achieve alleviation of seizures using medications. Patients with drug resitant epilepsy become candidates for surgical resection of brain tissue suspected to be the seizure onset zone (SOZ). Intracranial EEG (iEEG) data is collected from these patients to localize the seizure onset zone, which is done by manually or semi-automatically scanning through hours of iEEG recordings. iEEG data presents several challenges for the development of automated techniques such as high-dimensionality, non-stationarity, and heterogeneity of SOZ across patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have discovered iEEG biomarkers and developed ML methods to addresses two important clinicals challenges: (i) SOZ localization, and (ii) predicting seizure clustering. We observed that relative entropy, a bivariate iEEG feature which represents the similarity in brain activity between pairs of iEEG electrodes, is a suitable biomarker for the above tasks. Relative entropy also enables abstracting streams of iEEG data into time-evolving graphs - rendering the data suitable for application of graph theoretical techniques.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant publications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, Y. Cao, V. Kremen, V. Sladky, N. M. Gregg, P. M. Arnold, P. J. Karoly, D. R. Freestone, M. J. Cook, G. A. Worrell, R. K. Iyer (2023). &lt;a href=&#34;https://ieeexplore.ieee.org/document/10122733&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Individualized seizure cluster prediction using machine learning and chronic ambulatory intracranial EEG&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IEEE Transactions on NanoBioscience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;*, I. Balzekas*, V. Kremen, Y. Varatharajah, M. T. Kucewicz, R. K. Iyer, G. A. Worrell (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/epi.17067&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Leveraging electrophysiologic correlates of word encoding to map seizure onset zone in focal epilepsy: Task-dependent changes in epileptiform activity, spectral features, and functional connectivity&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Epilepsia&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Y. Varatharajah, M.J. Chong, &lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, B. M. Berry, B. Brinkmann, G. A. Worrell, R. K. Iyer (2017). &lt;a href=&#34;https://papers.nips.cc/paper/2017/file/fb3f76858cb38e5b7fd113e0bc1c0721-Paper.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;EEG-GRAPH: A factor graph-based model for capturing spatial, temporal, and observational relationships in electroencephalograms&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;(&lt;strong&gt;NeurIPS&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Summer Course 2020</title>
      <link>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/mlsc2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/mlsc2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This course was designed to provide an intuition for the fundamentals of basic machine learning models to students who have a high school level background in maths. It has over 12 hrs of lecture material along with an assignment for each lecture. Please find the lectures below. Feel free to reach out to me with any questions or suggestions or if you want access to the assignments!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kvsaboo.github.io/files/L01_MathReview.pdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 1: Maths review&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kvsaboo.github.io/files/L02_kNN_BayesRisk.pdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 2: k-Nearest Neighbor, Bayes Risk, Performance Metrics&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kvsaboo.github.io/files/L03_LinearLogisticRegression.pdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 3: Linear and Logistic Regression&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kvsaboo.github.io/files/L04_SVM_RandomForest.pdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 4: Support Vector Machines, Random Forest&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kvsaboo.github.io/files/L05_kMeans_GMM.pdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 5: Clustering (k-Means, Gaussian Mixture Model)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://kvsaboo.github.io/files/L06_PCA_etc.pdf&#34;&gt;Lecture 6: Principal Component Analysis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks to Tejal, Irena, Thanh, Abhi, Michelle for their enthusiastic participation in the course. Special thanks to Prakruthi for her feedback in developing the material!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microbiome</title>
      <link>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/microbiome_details/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/microbiome_details/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The microbiome &amp;ndash; the collection of microbes in and on our body - plays an important role in human health. Changes in the microbiome composition have been implicated in several diseases. Does the presence of certain microbes associate with disease?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We addressed this question in the context of liver cirrhosis-induced cognitive impairment. Microbiome data presents unique challenges such as high-dimensionality, low sample numbers, and sparsity. We used traditional ML methods combined with model interpretation techniques and biological pathway analysis to drive novel insights into how certain microbes might explain disease symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant publications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, N. Petrakov, A. Shamsaddini, A. Fagan, E. A. Gavis, M. Sikaroodi, S. McGeorge, P. Gillevet, R. K. Iyer, J. S. Bajaj (2022). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0168827821021838&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Stool microbiota are superior to saliva in distinguishing cirrhosis and hepatic encephalopathy using machine learning&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal of Hepatology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;*, A. Shamsaddini*, M. V. Iyer, C. Hu, A. Fagan, E. A. Gavis, M. B. White, M. Fuchs, D. M. Heuman, M. Sikaroodi, R. K. Iyer, P. M. Gillevet, J. S. Bajaj (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0168827820304578&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Sex is associated with differences in gut microbial composition and function in hepatic encephalopathy&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Journal of Hepatology&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Short term memory</title>
      <link>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/stm_details/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://kvsaboo.github.io/support/stm_details/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Which brain regions are involved in memory processing and what are the brain activity signatures of memory? Answering this question can potentially help in developing brain stimulation techniques that enhance memory in patients suffering from memory loss, for e.g., in traumatic brain injury.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We addressed the above question using intracranial EEG (iEEG) data collected from epilepsy patients as they performed a short term memory task. In the task, patients were requested to learn and recall lists of words, while iEEG data was collected when patients were shown the words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We developed automated techniques to identify implanted electrodes measuring memory related activity. The methods are orders of magnitude faster than currently used semi-automated techniques with over 95% accuracy. On data from over 100 people with more than 12,000 electrodes, the methods led to the discovery of a novel brain region for memory processing and helped predict individualized memory performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Relevant publications&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;C. Topcu, V. S. Marks, &lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, M. Lech, P. Nejedly, V. Kremen, G. A. Worrell, M T. Kucewicz (2022). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S2352396422003164&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Hotspot of human verbal memory encoding in the left anterior prefrontal cortex&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;eBioMedicine&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;V. S. Marks, &lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, C. Topcu, T. P. Thayib, P. Nejedly, V. Kremen, G. A. Worrell, M. T. Kucewicz (2021). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1053811921009101&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Independent dynamics of slow, intermediate, and fast intracranial EEG spectral activities during human memory formation&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;NeuroImage&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, Y. Varatharajah, B. M. Berry, V. Kremen, M. R. Sperling, K. A. Davis, B. C. Jobst, R. E. Gross, B. Lega, S. A. Sheth, G. A. Worrell, R. K. Iyer, M. T. Kucewicz (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-019-53925-5&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Unsupervised machine learning classification of electrophysiologically active electrodes during human cognitive task performance&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nature Scientific Reports&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;9&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;M. T. Kucewicz, &lt;strong&gt;K. V. Saboo&lt;/strong&gt;, B. M. Berry, V. Kremen, L. R. Miller, F. Khadjevand, C. S. Inman, P. Wanda, M. R. Sperling, R. Gorniak, K. A. Davis, B. C. Jobst, B. Lega, S. A. Sheth, D. S. Rizzuto, R. K. Iyer, M. J. Kahana, G. A. Worrell (2019). &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.eneuro.org/content/6/1/ENEURO.0214-18.2018&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Human verbal memory encoding is hierarchically distributed in a continuous processing stream&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;eNeuro&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;6.1&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
